Guide to the Robert Alexander Papers 1962-1987 MSS 114
Fales Library and Special Collections
Robert Alexander Papers
1962-1987
MSS 114
Fales Library and Special Collections
14.0 linear feet (41 boxes)
Alexander was born in 1943 in New York. He was a photographer closely connected with performance art and experimental dance during the late seventies and early eighties, and worked with choreographers such as Douglass Dunn, Simone Forti, and Yvonne Rainer. His photographs of dance and theatre performances appeared regularly in the Soho Weekly News in 1978 and 1979, and he collaborated with the dance critic and writer Sally Banes on the book: Terpsichore in Sneakers, which remains a standard text of postmodern dance. His photography thus documents an important period in the development of contemporary dance and performance art. In addition to his work on dance, Alexander was a keen observer and documenter of the city in which he spent all of his life. The collection contains hundreds of slides and prints of New York street scenes and architecture from the late sixties until just before Alexander's death in 1989. The Robert Alexander papers is an extensive collection of his photography and related materials.
Alexander, Robert, 1947-
Provenance
The Robert Alexander Papers were bequeathed to the Fales Library by the estate of Ann Beckerman, Robert Alexander's second wife. The transfer of materials, which included photographic prints, contact sheets and negatives, several boxes of slides, as well as personal papers and memorabilia, took place in January 2001 with the assistance of Dan Beckerman, Ann Beckerman's brother and the executor of her estate.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival materials.
Historical/Biographical Note:
Robert Alexander was born in Brooklyn on the 21st of November 1943. He spent most of his early life there, eventually working as a freelance photographer and photographer's assistant from various addresses, including Remsen Street in the downtown area of the city. He studied Art History at the University of Pennsylvania from 1961 to 1965 (but did not graduate) and did brief stints at the New School for Social Research (film production) and at the School of Visual Arts (16mm film editing). By the early seventies, Alexander had moved to Manhattan and had begun his work as a freelance photographer, though he continued to assist other photographers for several years. He also worked as a commercial photographer, doing catalogues and advertising for jewelry and clothing manufacturers.
Alexander's early portfolio work is at first tentatively formalist, but he quickly develops a strongly realist approach to subjects. He moves from photographing everyday, domestic objects to photographing people and street scenes. Though he retained his interest in still life photography all through his photographic career, sometimes photographing single objects in obsessive detail, it is as an observer of people in motion and interacting with a changing environment that Alexander is at his best. His photographs of New York streets, people, and architecture have that combination of intense engagement with and detachment from subjects that characterizes the work of many renowned documenters of modern city life. Alexander's slides and prints of New York City during the seventies and eighties are a lively record of a city undergoing intense change and they reveal a fascination both with the ordinariness of city life and the grandeur and strangeness of the city itself. He undertook several personal projects, photographing New York cabs and shop mannequins, and, over several years, scenes of the street from his apartment on 29th street. He also documented the building of the West Side Highway and took hundreds of slides of the Manhattan skyline.
Alexander's first resumes indicate that by the early seventies he had begun to think of himself as specializing in performance photography. His work had started to appear in various publications associated with the arts and he had collaborated with Sally Banes on the book: Terpsichore in Sneakers. His black and white photographs are given a special place in the book, accompanying individual chapters and also comprising a separate section at the end of the text. The spare, often stark simplicity of the photography suggests that Alexander had understood the tension between the singularity of the dancer's body and its sometimes violent, sometimes playful interaction with other bodies and objects. The choreographers and dancers he photographed for the book and for other publications had inherited a strong dance vocabulary from the avant-garde performers and choreographers of the fifties and sixties, but they were constantly seeking to break free of some of the constraints imposed upon modern dance by that vocabulary. These attempts to redefine movement and dance are perhaps best exemplified by the development of Contact Improvisation, with its mixture of randomness, spontaneity, and carefully focused give and take between dancers. Alexander frequently photographed Steve Paxton, who was instrumental in the development of this form, as well as the other choreographers and dancers of the collaborative group: Grand Union. His photographs of them are of performers who seem at times restrained and poised and at times utterly abandoned to movement and to contact with other dancers. His strongest street photographs share this quality with his dance pictures. He seems drawn to the vulnerability of bodies in a dynamic environment, and his work conveys something of the dancer's desire both to control spaces and to be abandoned to them.
While Alexander did not achieve the broad recognition of some of his contemporaries such as Peter Moore, his work is an important contribution to the documentation of experimental dance and performance of the seventies and eighties. He photographed most of the major experimental choreographers, dancers, and performers of the period, including Stuart Sherman, Kenneth King, Simone Forti, David Gordon, Valda Setterfield, Laura Foreman, Carter Frank, Yvonne Rainer, Steve Paxton, Douglass Dunn, Rudy Perez, Meredith Monk, Trisha Brown, Lucinda Childs, and many others. He also photographed musicians and actors, such as the then emerging Tom Waits and the already famous Peter Ustinov.
By the mid-eighties Alexander was doing less and less dance photography and more photography of the city. The collection includes thousands of slides of Manhattan dating from this period, many of which reveal Alexander's interest in ordinary street scenes and people. Most, however, are of the city's skyline and monolithic architecture, and testify to the photographer's obsession with the city that he lived in all of his life and which he left only briefly as a young man. Alexander died on the 8th of October, 1989.
Scope and Content Note
The Robert Alexander Papers are a part of the Downtown Collection at the Fales Library, New York University. The Fales Library is the primary special collections division of the NYU libraries, housing nearly 200,000 volumes of English and American literature from 1700 to the present. Strengths of the collection include the development of the English and American novel, with an emphasis on the Gothic and the Victorian novel.
The Robert Alexander Papers comprise mainly photographs, contact sheets and negatives, and slides. There is one box of personal papers, correspondence, and memorabilia, and two boxes containing other media, such as 16mm and Super 8 films and audio cassettes. The negatives and contact sheets have been kept in chronological order, as Alexander had organized them, and the prints and slides have been arranged alphabetically. There are three boxes of unprocessed material at the end of the collection.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
SERIES I: Prints
Subseries A: Dance and Performance Prints
This subseries contains 4 boxes, ordered alphabetically, of dance and performance-related photographs. Box 4 is oversize.
Subseries B: Prints for the Soho Weekly News
This is a series of prints, arranged chronologically, of work done for the Soho Weekly News. Copies of the tearsheets from the newspaper can be found in Series IV, box 38, folder 38.
Subseries C: Celebrity and other portraits
Amongst the photographs in this subseries are portraits of Alvin Ailey, Tom Waits, Lucinda Childs, Peter Ustinov, Peter Boyle, Laura Foreman, Ann Beckerman, and Robert Alexander. The subseries also contains several poignant photographs of laboratory chimpanzees taken for an article in the NYU Physician.
Subseries D: Portfolios and other personal work
Boxes 7 through 11 contain prints from Alexander's portfolios. These photographs were not clearly dated by the photographer. Since the subject matter is varied and the dates uncertain the prints have been boxed in no particular order. Wherever possible however, prints that were grouped together by the photographer have been kept together in the collection. Box 11 contains oversize prints.
SERIES II: Slides
Some of the slides in the collection were arranged in sleeves by the photographer, but thousands were in labeled and unlabelled slide boxes. It was extremely difficult to detect any order in the slides and so they have been arranged alphabetically and thematically. The embossed dates on the slides seem more or less accurate but cannot be relied upon (since some slides may have been processed some time after shoots).
Subseries A: Dance and Performance
Boxes 12 through18 are arranged alphabetically. Of special interest are several sheets of slides, in order, of Stuart Sherman's Eleventh Spectacle (Box 16).
Subseries B: Events
Slides in this subseries are arranged roughly chronologically, though dates are uncertain. Of special interest are slides of the John Lennon observance in Central Park, and those of Thelonius Monk's funeral.
Subseries C: Portraits
The box of portraits in this subseries includes shots of Alvin Ailey, Philippe Petite, Peter Ustinov, and Tom Waits.
Subseries D: Projects: 1973 - 1987 and other personal work
These slides are arranged thematically and chronologically where possible. They comprise several ongoing projects, most of which document some aspect of life in Manhattan. Of special interest are the slides of the Alex Katz mural in the Attorney General's office. Box 25 appears to be a selection made by Alexander and the slides have been kept in the order in which he arranged them.
Subseries E: City people, 1973 - 1983
This is one box of slides, arranged more or less chronologically.
Subseries F: City scenes, 1980 - 1986
The slides span a six year period and have been arranged more or less chronologically.
Subseries G: Nature
Boxes 31 through 33 are arranged roughly chronologically.
Subseries H: Commercial work
This is one box of slides of work done for jewelry and footwear catalogues. It represents a fraction of Alexander's commercial work in this field. The remainder have been roughly processed and boxed separately.
SERIES III: Negatives and contact sheets
Alexander organized his negatives and contact sheets chronologically. This arrangement has been retained as far as possible.
SERIES IV: Printed and other materials
Subseries A: Printed material, memorabilia, correspondence, ephemera
This subseries comprises two boxes of material, one of which is oversize (box 39).
SERIES V: Motion Picture Film Material
Subseries A: Access Copies
Subseries B: Originals
Researchers are limited to Subseries A: Access Copies.
SERIES VI: Videotape Recordings
Subseries A: Access Copies
SERIES VII: Sound Recordings
Subseries A: Access Copies
Subseries B: Originals
Researchers are limited to Subseries A: Access Copies, or ask a Fales archivist.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically by subject but sometimes chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into 4 series.
Series I: Prints
Series II: Slides
Series III: Negatives and Contact Sheets
Series IV: Printed and Other Materials
Series V: Motion Picture Film Material
Series VI: Videotape Recordings
Series VII: Sound Recordings
Related Material at the Fales Library and Special Collections
The Judson Memorial Church Archive
Wendy Perron's "Concepts in Performance," In The Soho Weekly News (1976-78)
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Ailey, Alvin; Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater.; Antin, Eleanor; Atwood, Geri; Banes, Sally; Beardsley, Bettany; Beckerman, Ann; Big Apple Circus.; Boyle, Peter, 1933-; Brown, Trisha, 1936-; Childs, Lucinda; Chong, Ping; Chuma, Yoshiko; Cumming, Ann; Cummings, Blondell; De Groat, Andrew; Dunas, William; Dunn, Douglas, 1942-; Foreman, Laura; Forti, Simone; Frank, Carter; Gardner, Barbara; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997; Glass, Philip; Goldblum, Jeff, 1952-; Gordh, Bill; Gordon, David, 1936-; Grand Union (Performance group).; Halprin, Anna; Hay, Deborah, 1941-; Jacobowitz, Diane; Jaroslow, Risa; Joyce, Donald; Kast, Maggie; Katz, Alex, 1927-; Kaye, Pooh; King, Kenneth, 1948-; Kipper Kids (Group of artists).; Kroesen, Jill; Kushner, Robert, 1949-; Landry, Richard; Lord, Carolyn; Malpede, John; McLean, Bruce; Monk, Meredith; No Theatre (Theater group).; Overlie, Mary; Paxton, Steve; Perez, Rudy; Rainer, Yvonne, 1934-; Reitz, Dana; Roberts, Erik; Rockettes (Dance company).; Rudner, Sara; Selmier, Dean; Setterfield, Valda; Sherman, Stuart; Smith, Nancy Stark; Squat Theatre (Theater group).; Tanaka, Min; Taylor, Paul, 1930-; Ustinov, Peter; Van Riper, Peter; Waits, Tom, 1949-; We, Ellen; Whitman, Sylvia; Woodberry, David; Zaloom, Paul; 16mm.; Audiocassettes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Dance photography.; Dance |v Pictorial works.; Dancers |v Portraits.; Ephemera.; Financial records.; Landscape photography.; New York (N.Y.); Photographs.; Photography, Artistic.; Portrait photography.; Record covers.; Super 8.; Tear sheets.
- Series I: Prints
  - Subseries A: Dance prints
    Scope and Content note
    Series I: Subseries contains 4 boxes, ordered alphabetically, of dance and performance-related photographs. Box 4 is oversize.
    - Trisha Brown: Figure Eight, rehearsal, 1973 (2 prints) Primary Accumulations, rehearsal, 1973 (1 print) Water Motor, performance, 1979 (7 prints) Interview portrait, Jan 1974 (1 print), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lucinda Childs: Melody Excerpt, rehearsal, 1978 (4 prints) Katema, performance, 1978 (2 prints) Dance, rehearsal, 1979 (2 prints), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Yoshiko Chuma, 9 Mar 1980 (2 prints) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Douglas Dunn: 101, performance exhibition, 1974 (4 prints) Lazy Madge, performance, 1976 (4 prints) Coquina, performance, 1979 (2 prints), 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Simone Forti at Fordham, Apr 1976 (10 prints) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Simone Forti at St Marks, May 1976 (6 prints) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Simone Forti and Peter Van Riper at the Museum of Modern Art, Aug 1978 (11 prints) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Carter Frank (with Maggie Kast et al), May 1974 (2 prints) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - David Gordon: Not necessarily Recognizable Objectives, performance, 1978 (5 prints) What Happened, performance,1978 (2 prints) Times Four, performance with Valda Setterfield, 1976 (3 prints) David Gordon/Pick Up Co., performance, Apr 1978 (2 prints) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bill Gordh and John Malpede, Dead Dog and Lonely Horse, Nov 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Grand Union: Improvisatory performance, 1974 (8 prints) Rehearsal, June 1975 (3 prints) Performance at La Mama, Apr 1976 (2 prints), 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Deborah Hay: Rehearsal, Feb 1979 (1 print) Solo performance, Feb 1979 (1 print) The Grand Dance, workshop, 1979 (2 prints) (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Diane Jacobowitz, performance, May/June 1980 (2 prints) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Risa Jaroslow, 21 Oct 1978 (1 print) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Pooh Kaye, Blur, Mar 1982 (1 print) (see also slides) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Kenneth King: With Carter Frank, performance, 8 Dec 1978 (6 prints) Performance, 8 Dec 1978 (1 print) Word Raid, performance at St Marks benefit, 1 Jan 1979 (1 print), 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Meredith Monk: Education of the Girlchild, performance, 1973 (5 prints) Education of the Girlchild, performance, 1979 (2 prints), 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Meredith Monk and Ping Chong, Paris, performance, 1974 (8 prints) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Multi-gravitational Experimental Group: Performance, Dec 1973 (21 prints) Performance, May 1974 (2 prints), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Steve Paxton: Backwater: Twosome, performance, 1978 (3 prints) With Nancy Stark-Smith, Contact Improvisation, performance, 1978 (1 print) Contact Improvisation, performance, 1978 (2 prints) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Steve Paxton with Grand Union, 1973 (1 print) - photograph by Gwen Thomas (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Rudy Perez, rehearsal and performance, Dec 1973 (15 prints) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Yvonne Rainer, New Version of Convalescent Dance, performance, 1979 (2 prints) (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Paul Taylor, Arden Court, Apr 1982 (1 print) (see slides) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Terpsichore in Sneakers: Yvonne Rainer, Trio A, performance, 1978 (6 prints) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Terpsichore in Sneakers: Deborah Hay, The Grand Dance, 1979 Lucinda Childs, Katema, 1978 Lucinda Childs, Melody Excerpt, 1978 Meredith Monk and Ping Chong, Paris, 1974 Meredith Monk, Education of the Girlchild, 1973 Kenneth King, Wor(l)d (T)rade, 1978 Kenneth King, RadeoA.C.tiv(ID)ty, 1978 Douglas Dunn, Coquina, 1979 Douglas Dunn, 101, 1974 Douglas Dunn, improv., 1974 Grand Union, improv., 1974, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Terpsichore in Sneakers: Simone Forti, Big Room, 1976 Grand Union, Improvisation, 1974 Simone Forti, Fountain Huddle, 1978 Steve Paxton, Backwater: Twosome, 1978 Trisha Brown, Water Motor, 1979 David Gordon, Not Necessarily Recognizable Objectives, 1978 Deborah Hay, solo, 1979 Lucinda Childs, Dance, rehearsal, 1979 Meredith Monk, Education of the Girlchild, 1979 Kenneth King, Word Raid, 1978 Douglas Dunn, Lazy Madge, 1976, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Terpsichore in Sneakers: Simone Forti, Phoenix, 1978 Simone Forti and Peter Van Riper, Big Room, 1979 Yvonne Rainer, New Version of Convalescent Dance, 1979 Steve Paxton and Nancy Stark-Smith, 1978 Trisha Brown, Primary Accumulation, 1973 Trisha Brown, Water Motor, 1979 David Gordon, Times Four, 1976 David Gordon, What Happened, 1978 David Gordon, Not Necessarily Recognizable Objectives, 1978 Deborah Hay, solo, 1979, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Ellen Webb, dance relaxation techniques, Mar 1979 (1 print) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Bettany Beardsley, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Peter Boyle, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Trisha Brown, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Lucinda Childs, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Lucinda Childs, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Lucinda Childs, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Lucinda Childs, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Yoshiko Chuma, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Andy DeGroat, Philip Glass, Dickie Landry, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Andy DeGroat, Philip Glass, Dickie Landry, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Andy DeGroat, Philip Glass, Dickie Landry, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Philip Glass, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Dickie Landry, Philip Glass, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Dickie Landry, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Andy DeGroat and dancers, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Shelley and Denman at Ear Inn, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Shelley and Denman, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Denman, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Shelley and Denman, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Bill Dunas dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Bill Dunas dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Bill Dunas dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Doug Dunn and Dave Woodberry, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Doug Dunn and Dave Woodberry, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Doug Dunn and Sara Rudner, undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Simone Forti and Peter Van Riper, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Peter Van Riper, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Peter Van Riper, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Peter Van Riper, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Carter Frank, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Carter Frank, Maggie Kast, et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Carter Frank, Maggie Kast, et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Friday 13th at MoMA, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Friday 13th at MoMA, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Friday 13th at MoMA, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Friday 13th at MoMA, undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Barbara Gardner, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Barbara Gardner, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Barbara Gardner, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Barbara Gardner, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Allen Ginsberg, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - St Marks Benefit, undated (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Jeff Goldblum, undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Jeff Goldblum, undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Jeff Goldblum, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - David Gordon and Valda Setterfield, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - David Gordon and Valda Setterfield, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Grand Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Anna Halprin, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Diane Jacobowitz dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Diane Jacobowitz dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Diane Jacobowitz, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Diane Jacobowitz, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Diane Jacobowitz, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Diane Jacobowitz et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Diane Jacobowitz et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Diane Jacobowitz dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Diane Jacobowitz et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Diane Jacobowitz dancer, undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Alex Katz mural, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Alex Katz mural, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Alex Katz mural, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Pooh Kaye et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Pooh Kaye et al, undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Kenneth King, undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Kipper Kids, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Kipper Kids, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Robert Kushner's New York Hat Line, undated (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Robert Kushner's New York Hat Line, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Robert Kushner, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Robert Kushner, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)